Guide to the Henry J. Dannenbaum Papers, 1910-1912 MS 736
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Henry J. Dannenbaum Papers
1910-1912
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Dannenbaum, Henry J.
MS 736
.75 Linear Feet 2 boxes
This collection contains correspondence, news clippings, reports, publications, court documents, and organizational materials documenting some of Henry J. Dannenbaum's work as Special Assistant to the Attorney General, investigating violations of the Mann Act (The White-Slave Traffic Act).
Biographical / Historical
Henry J. Dannenbaum was born on October 30, 1871 in East Columbia, Brazoria County, Texas. He attended Henry College in Virginia, graduating in 1890. He studied law privately and was admitted to the bar in Sequin, Texas in 1892. He married Sadie Bowman around 1888, and the two had five children. Dannenbaum became a prominent lawyer and prosecutor in Houston, Texas, and served on the Houston School Board - both as a member and president - from 1904 to 1907.
Dannenbaum was an outspoken critic of white-slave trafficking, particularly among young immigrants. He was active in lobbying for the passage of the Mann Act, which made it illegal to transport women across state lines for immoral purposes. After the law was passed, Dannenbaum accepted an appointment as a Special Assistant to the Attorney General (Wickersham) to investigate violations of the Mann Act. During his year with the Department of Justice he successfully brought a number of violators to justice. He voluntarily retired from his position as Special Assistant and returned to his practice in Houston full-time.
In 1915, the governor appointed him to the position of judge for the 61st District Court in Houston. He was the first person of Jewish descent to sit on the state bench in Texas. He was president of the Hebrew Congregation Beth Israel of Houston and of District 7, Independent Order of B'nai B'rith, as well as a member of Social Services Foundation of Houston.
Dannanbaum died August 23, 1940 in Houston.
Some parts excerpted from:
https://www.jewishsouth.org/system/files/sjh_v._7_2004_stone.pdf http://www.isjl.org/texas-houston-encyclopedia.html
Scope and Contents
Two boxes of correspondence, news clippings, reports, publications, court documents, and organizational papers document Henry J. Dannenbaum's time as Special Assistant to the Attorney General of the United States working to enforce the Mann Act (White-Slave Traffic Act).
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Papers were donated by Glen Rosenbaum, Feb. 2, 2018
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series: Series I: Correspondence Series II: Court Documents Series III: News Clips Series IV: Organizational Materials Series V: Publications Series VI: Reports
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life; prostitution; Law and legislation; Emigration and immigration; Courts
Document Types
personal correspondence
- Series I: Correspondence, 1910-1912
  - Letter from Samuel Frenkel, 1910-03 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with Martin Zielonka, 1911-01-1911-08 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Harry Cutler, 1911-03 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with P.W. Horn, 1911-03 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with G.A. levi, 1911-03-1911-06 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with S.H. London, 1911-03-1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with Stanley W. Finch, 1911-03-1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence re: Mann Act in relation to Railroad Ticket Agents, 1911-04-1911-05 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with George Wickersham (Attorney General), 1911-04-1911-06 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with Robert Lovett, 1911-05 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence from Emil Nathan, 1911-05-1911-06 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with Leon Zolotkof/Jewish Daily News, 1911-05-1911-06 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with Joseph Hirsh, 1911-05 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with A.L. Schailt, 1911-05-18-1911-06-08 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence with William Alexander Coote, 1911-05-1911-06 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with James Bronson Reynolds and Charles Whitman (NYC D.A.), 1911-05-1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence with William Williams, 1911-05-1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence with Archibald Marx, 1911-05-1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence with Leon Schwraz, 1911-05-1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence with General Correspondence, 1911-06-1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence with Edward Janney/The National Vigilance Committe, 1911-06-1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence from Dannenbaum requesting assistance from community leaders, 1911-06-1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence with Adolf Kraus (B'nai B'rith), 1911-06-1912-01 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence with Jacob Furth, 1911-05-1911-06 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence with Frederick Whitin, 1911-06 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence with Acting Commissioner of Immigration, 1911-06 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letter from Miss Ray Perlman, 1911-06-22 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence with Rabbi Henry Cohen, 1911-06 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence with Gorham Press, 1911-06 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence with Harry Parkin, 1911-06-1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence with D. D. Walton, 1911-06-1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence with David M. Bressler, 1911-06-1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence with J.L. Magnes, 1911-06-1911-09 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence with Bernard Richards of Jewish Community, NYC, 1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence with Otto Taub, 1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence with publications, attempting to get article published, 1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence with Samuel E. Pents, 1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence regarding medical attention for a girl, 1911-07 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Letter to E.J. Brennan from S.J.B, 1911-07-05 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence with Grace H. Dodge, 1911-07-15 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Letter to Jacob Dannenbaum, 1911-07-17 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letter to Dannenbaum re: Fanny Cohen matter, 1911-07-22 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with David Laser, 1911-07 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Telegram to Jacob Dannenbaum, 1911-07-27 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letter re: Savina matter, 1911-07-28 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence re: procuring importers (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series II: Court Documents, 1910-1911
  - Indictments (Wagner, Clarke, and Hoke) and Statement (Kaplan), 1910-06-1911-07 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Informant Statements from Jules Simon re: M. Cohen, 1911-07 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - U.S. v. Samuel Kerber, Circuit Court for the Southern District of NY, 1911-05 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Case Notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series III: News Clips, 1911-06-18
  - New York Herald press clip, 1911-06-18 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Organizational Materials, n.d.
  - Tentative plan for organized suppression of white-slave traffic, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series V: Publications, 1910-1911
  - THE LAW: Proposed for the Suppression of the White-Slave Traffic, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Outlook, 1911-07-15 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Brief Statement of the Conclusions and Recommendations of the Immigration Commission, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Series VI: Reports, n.d.
  - Importation of Aliens for Prostitution, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Index to reports on white-slave cases (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Harboring Women for Immoral Purposes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 18)